Welcome to another episode of Five
Minute Physiology with Dr. Andy Galpin.
>> Whether you're a high performing athlete
or just interested in general health and
longevity, your resting heart rate is
one of the most critical pieces of
information you should pay attention to.
There's a reason your doctor measures it
every single time you go in for a visit.
We measure it in our clients as often as
possible. It gives us great insights
into overall health, cardiovascular
fitness, whether you're training too
much or too little, got sick, is are
experiencing bad sleep, and a number of
other factors. And so, how do we make
sure that our resting heart rate's in a
great spot? Well, we need to first start
by understanding what a good resting
heart rate even is. See, if you're like
one of the hummingbirds that's currently
outside of my window, you might be
cruising around at 1,000 or even 1,200
beats per minute. If you're a whale or a
large mammal, you might be at five or
six. Human babies, surprising enough,
are actually oftentimes 150 to even 200
beats per minute, and that's completely
normal. But most average adults are
going to be sitting in the 60 to 80
beats per minute range. That said, high
performing endurance athletes are really
commonly in the low 30s or even 40s. I
know personally many that I have coached
are in the 32 to 35 range. Now, I don't
know the official world record here, but
there have been documented cases of
endurance athletes being as high or as
low rather as the high 20s. And there's
one legendary story of an 80 plus year
old man with a resting heart rate of 26
beats per minute, though I personally
can't attest to the accuracy of that
legend. So, if your resting heart rate's
a little bit higher than you'd like, we
need to actually start by understanding
why it's there in the first place. Let
me go back to the basics of
cardiovascular physiology here. See,
your heart rate is determined by
something called your cardiac output.
Now, we often express this in liters per
minute, and it's basically how many
liters of blood we're moving throughout
our heart in a given minute. Why does
that matter? I'll come back to that in
one second. Cardiac output is generally
fixed. So, at rest, while you're sitting
here watching this highly entertaining
video, you might have a cardiac output
of 3 to four, maybe up to 5 L per
minute. Whether you got more or less fit
may or may not change that. So the
demand for oxygen at rest is pretty much
the same. How you get that demand though
is variable. You can switch this. So
cardiac output is determined by two
factors. It is your heart rate
multiplied by your stroke volume. Your
heart rate is how many times you're
beating per minute. Your stroke volume
is of course how much blood is pumping
out of your heart per pump. So quick
math here. If you were to increase your
stroke volume, this would mean your
resting heart rate can go down so that
your cardiac output stays the same.
Friends, that is the exact game we're
playing. I want you to conceptualize
this a little bit. So let me give you
some exact numbers. Let's imagine at
rest your stroke volume was 2 to three
ounces. But when you started exercising
that increased to seven or eight ounces
and since you're doing that your heart
rate is also elevated. For many people,
let's just say your maximum heart rate
is 180 beats per minute. At 180 beats
per minute, you're actually beating
three to four times per second. And
every time you're doing that, you got
about 25 to 30 ounces that are coming
out. Another way to think about that is
it's about a pound and a half to two
pounds of blood coming out of your heart
per pump. But because you're doing that
for 60 seconds, you got to multiply that
all by 60, which means you're kicking
out about 85 pounds of blood in a given
minute. That is a tremendous amount of
work that your little heart is doing. If
you were to put yourself through all
that, your body would eventually adapt
and it would start saying, "We have a
high demand for cardiac output." Now, it
actually can't increase its maximal
heart rate. That would be tough. In
fact, one of the limiters that you see
is if our heart rate gets too high, we
don't have enough time to fill blood in
the heart in between pumps to then push
more blood back out. So, maximum heart
rate will stay the same. Our only option
here is to increase our stroke volume.
By doing that,
even at rest, we have a higher stroke
volume, which means again, we kick out
more blood per pump, which allows our
resting heart rate to come down when our
cardiac output is fixed. Go back a few
minutes. That's what we started the
conversation with. Right? Now that we
understand the basic mechanisms, what
insights can we have about getting this
stuff to happen? So what do I mean by
that? Let me give you one more equation.
Let's just say that cardiac output is
3.8 L per minute. A very common number
for an average adult. If your stroke
volume was only 2 ounces, this would
mean your resting heart rate has to be
70 beats per minute to give you that 3.8
L per minute total. But if you went and
increase a stroke volume to three, this
would allow your resting heart rate to
drop all the way to 43. So the
functional difference, friends, from
going from a resting heart rate of 70
beats per minute to 43 beats per minute
is simply giving yourself one more ounce
per pump. How do we get that done? Well,
now that you understand why it happened
in the first place, the options will
become far clearer. The best thing you
could possibly do is exercise. And you
have a lot of options with that. There
is no magic recipe or protocol. Trust me
friends, if there was, I would tell you
because the reality of it is the heart
is responding to everything you're
doing. You want to think about endurance
exercise though as your first stop on
this journey. Highintensity exercise is
awesome. It is particularly effective at
increasing what is called preload and
stretching. This means the amount of
blood that's being pumped into your
heart. Remember, your muscle and your
heart works just like your muscles in
the rest of your body. If it's
stretched, it wants to contract really
hard. So, if you send a bunch of blood
flying into your heart really fast, your
left ventricle, the bottom side, which
is what kicks your blood actually into
circulation, will get stretched really
hard and really fast, causing it to
contract really hard. This gets more
blood out per pump because it's
squeezing with more intensity. So,
high-intensity exercise is really
effective at that. Now, longer duration,
low intensity, con continuous, steady
state stuff, however you like to phrase
it, is also effective. You'll have
additional benefits there of increasing
total blood volume, which you may not
realize is one of the single most
important adaptations to all endurance
exercise. More blood, more preload, more
stretch, higher stroke volume, lower
resting heart rate. You can do either
one of these, only high intensity, only
lower intensity, or you could do a
combination. There is no current
research that suggests one of them is
fundamentally far better than the other
one. So, whatever fits your lifestyle
and personal preferences will work
there. A third thing you'd want to
consider would be strength training or
resistance exercise. Not nearly
effective as effective as endurance
exercise for stroke volume, but it does
have benefits for the left ventricle.
Can improve left ventricle size in the
good way as well as that contractility
or strength. If it was me, and I do
advise many clients on this, I would
probably do a combination of all three
styles of exercise because we get
different benefits there. A lot of
overlap, and plus, we have all the other
myriad of benefits we get from these
forms of exercise. Now, if you've done
all that and you still have a higher
resting heart than you'd like, couple of
other things to think about. First, it
could be related to things like stress,
bad sleep, or even a clinical sleep
disorder, or things like breathing
mechanics. If you're struggling to
breathe, you're going to have to breathe
more frequently to get things moving
through your system, and your heart rate
will respond to that. If it's none of
those things, then it could simply be
genetic. And you know what? You might
not have anything to worry about. So,
while I want you all to push the pace
and try to maximize your overall health
and performance, I also don't want you
to be freaked out by it and to worry
unnecessarily if you're doing all the
big things right in your lifestyle and
health and practice. I hope that was
informative and it helped. I'd love to
hear any progress that you make. And
thanks for checking out another episode
of 5minute Physiology. If you enjoyed
this and want to keep learning more
about human health and performance,
consider signing up for the Catalyst.
That's my completely free newsletter
where we share information about places
I've learned from, great books,
podcasts, social media people to follow,
and other ways to stay upto-date with
the most recent evidenceinformed
approaches in this field. I'll put a
link to that newsletter in the
description below as well as pinned to
the top comments and I'll see you there.